Way before the first selfie,
قديماً قبل أول صورة سيلفي،
the ancient Greeks and Romans had a myth
كان لليونانيون والرومانيون القدماء أسطورة
about someone a little too obsessed with his own image.
عن شخص كان مهووساً قليلا بصورته
In one telling,
فى إحدى الروايات،
Narcissus was a handsome guy wandering the world in search of someone to love.
كان نارسيسيوس شخصا وسيما يسافر حول العالم بحثاً عن شخص ليحبه،
After rejecting a nymph named Echo,
بعد أن رفض حورية تدعى"إيكو" أي الصدى،
he caught a glimpse of his own reflection in a river,
التقطت عيناه لمحة لانعكاس صورته في النهر،
and fell in love with it.
فوقع فى حب صورته.
Unable to tear himself away,
ولعجزه عن انتزاع نفسه بعيدا،
Narcissus drowned.
غرق نارسيسيوس.
A flower marked the spot of where he died, and we call that flower the Narcissus.
ونبتت زهرة مكان موته وتمت تسميتها باسم نارسيسيوس أي النرجس.
The myth captures the basic idea of narcissism,
الأسطورة توضح الفكرة الأساسية للنرجسية
elevated and sometimes detrimental self-involvement.
الترفع وأحيانا حب الذات المؤذي للنفس.
But it's not just a personality type that shows up in advice columns.
لكنها لا تنحصر في نوع شخصية تظهر فى مقالات النصائح.
It's actually a set of traits classified and studied by psychologists.
إنها فى الحقيقة مجموعة من السمات مصنفة ويُبحث فيها من قبل علماء النفس.
The psychological definition of narcissism is an inflated, grandiose self-image.
التعريف العلمى للنرجسية هي صورة للنفس متكلفة ومبالغ فيها.
To varying degrees, narcissists think they're better looking,
وبدرجات مختلفة يعتقد النرجسيون أنهم أفضل مظهرأ
smarter,
وأذكى
and more important than other people,
وأكثر أهمية من الآخرين
and that they deserve special treatment.
وبأنهم يستحقون معاملة خاصة.
Psychologists recognize two forms of narcissism as a personality trait:
يصنف علماء النفس النرجسية كصفة شخصية إلى صنفين
grandiose and vulnerable narcissism.
نرجسية فخامة و نرجسية هشة.
There's also narcissistic personality disorder,
هناك أيضاً اضطراب نرجسى فى الشخصية،
a more extreme form, which we'll return to shortly.
و هي حالة أكثر خطورة سنعود لها لاحقاً
Grandiose narcissism is the most familiar kind,
نرجسية الفخامة هى النوع الأكثر شيوعاً،
characterized by extroversion,
تصنف بالانفتاح على الآخرين
dominance,
و السيطرة،
and attention seeking.
والبحث عن إثارة الانتباه.
Grandiose narcissists pursue attention and power,
نرجسيو الفخامة يسعون إلى جذب الانتباه و السلطة،
sometimes as politicians,
وأحياناً كسياسيين،
celebrities,
أو مشاهير،
or cultural leaders.
أو قادة ثقافيين.
Of course, not everyone who pursues these positions of power is narcissistic.
بالطبع، ليس كل من يسعى خلف هذه المناصب هو شخصٌ نرجسي.
Many do it for very positive reasons,
العديد يفعلون ذلك لأسباب ايجابية،
like reaching their full potential,
مثل الوصول إلى أقصى إمكانياتهم،
or helping make people's lives better.
أو المساعدة في تحسين حياة الناس.
But narcissistic individuals seek power
لكنّ الأشخاص النرجسيون يسعون إلى القوة
for the status and attention that goes with it.
من أجل الموقع والاهتمام اللذان يأتيان معها.
Meanwhile, vulnerable narcissists can be quiet and reserved.
من ناحية أخرى، يكون النرجسيون الهشون هادئين ومتحفظين.
They have a strong sense of entitlement,
لديهم حس عالٍ من الاستحقاق،
but are easily threatened or slighted.
لكن يسهل تهديدهم و إهانتهم.
In either case, the dark side of narcissism shows up over the long term.
و فى كلا الحالتين، يظهر الجانب المظلم للنرجسية على المدى الطويل.
Narcissists tend to act selfishly,
و يميل النرجسيون إلى التصرف بأنانية،
so narcissistic leaders may make risky or unethical decisions,
حيث قد يتخذ القادة النرجسيون قرارات فيها مجازفة أو غير أخلاقية،
and narcissistic partners may be dishonest or unfaithful.
كما يمكن أن يكون الشركاء النرجسيون مخادعين أوغير مخلصين.
When their rosy view of themselves is challenged,
وعندما يتحدّى أحد نظرتهم الوردية لأنفسهم،
they can become resentful and aggressive.
فمن الممكن أن يصبحوا ممتعضين وعدوانيين.
It's like a disease where the sufferers feel pretty good,
إنها كالمرض حيث يشعر المرضى أنهم أصحاء،
but the people around them suffer.
لكن الناس حولهم يعانون.
Taken to the extreme,
وفي أقصى حالاتها
this behavior is classified as a psychological disorder
يصنف هذا السلوك كاضطراب نفسي
called narcissistic personality disorder.
يدعى الإضطراب النرجسي النفسي.
It affects one to two percent of the population,
وهو يصيب 1% إلى 2% من السكان،
more commonly men.
وخاصة الرجال.
It is also a diagnosis reserved for adults.
كما إنه تشخيص يقتصر على البالغين فقط.
Young people, especially children, can be very self-centered,
الصغار، خصوصاً الأطفال، من الممكن أن يكونوا مهتمين بأنفسهم فقط،
but this might just be a normal part of development.
لكن هذا من الممكن أن يكون مرحلة طبيعية من النمو.
The fifth edition of the American Psychiatric Association's
في الإصدار الخامس من كتاب الجمعية النفسية الأمريكية
Diagnostic and Statistical Manual
و في دليل التشخيص والإحصاء
describes several traits associated with narcissistic personality disorder.
تعطي سمات عديدة مرتبطة بالإضطراب النرجسي النفسي.
They include a grandiose view of oneself,
تشمل نظرة متفاخرة للنفس،
problems with empathy,
ومشاكل بالتعاطف
a sense of entitlement,
وشعور بالاستحقاق
and a need for admiration or attention.
و الحاجة للإعجاب والاهتمام.
What makes these trait a true personality disorder
وما يجعل هذه السمات اضطراباً حقيقياً للشخصية
is that they take over people's lives and cause significant problems.
هي أنها تسيطر على حياة الناس وتتسبب في مشاكل مهمة.
Imagine that instead of caring for your spouse or children,
تخيل بدلا من العناية برفيقك أو أطفالك،
you used them as a source of attention or admiration.
تستغلهم كمصدر للاهتمام والإعجاب بك.
Or imagine that instead of seeking
أو تصور أنك بدلاً من البحث
constructive feedback about your performance,
عن معلومات بناءة حول أدائك،
you instead told everyone who tried to help you
ستخبر جميع من حاول مساعدتك
that they were wrong.
بأنهم كانوا مخطئين.
So what causes narcissism?
حسنا ولكن ما هو سبب النرجسية؟
Twin studies show a strong genetic component,
أظهرت دراسة التوائم وجود عامل جيني قوي.
although we don't know which genes are involved.
مع عدم معرفتنا بالجينات المسببة لذلك.
But environment matters, too.
و كذلك فمواضيع البيئة تؤثر ايضا.
Parents who put their child on a pedestal
فالوالدان اللذان ينجبان طفلهما ليدللاه ويرفعاه
can foster grandiose narcissism.
يقومان بتعزيز النرجسبة المتعالية.
And cold, controlling parents can contribute to vulnerable narcissism.
والأبوان الباردان المسيطران يساهمان في تعزيز النرجسية الهشة.
Narcissism also seems to be higher
ويبدو أن النرجسية أعلى في
in cultures that value individuality and self-promotion.
المجتمعات التي تقدر الفردية والترقية الذاتية
In the United States, for example,
مثلا، في الولايات المتحدة،
narcissism as a personality trait has been rising since the 1970s,
زادت النرجسية كصفة شخصية منذ السبعينيات،
when the communal focus of the 60s
عندما أخلى التركيز الاجتماعي في الستينيات
gave way to the self-esteem movement
مكانه لحركات احترام الفردية
and a rise in materialism.
و صعود القيم المادية،
More recently, social media has multiplied the possibilities for self-promotion,
و قامت وسائل الإعلام مؤخراً بمضاعفة احتمالات تقدير الذات،
though it's worth noting
رغم أهمية ملاحظة
that there's no clear evidence that social media causes narcissism.
عدم وجود دليل واضح على تسبب الإعلام الإجتماعي في النرجسية.
Rather, it provides narcissists a means to seek social status and attention.
بل توفر للنرجسيين وسائل للبحث عن موقع اجتماعي واهتمام أكبر.
So can narcissists improve on those negative traits?
إذاً، هل يستطيع النرجسيون التطور بهذه الصفات السلبية؟
Yes!
نعم!
Anything that promotes honest reflection on their own behavior
كل ما يحسن الانعكاس الجيد في سلوكهم
and caring for others,
و الاهتمام بالآخرين،
like psychotherapy or practicing compassion towards others, can be helpful.
مثل العلاج النفسي أو تجربة التعاطف مع الآخرين يمكن أن يساعد كثيرا.
The difficulty is it can be challenging
إن الصعوبة هي في أنها تكون تحديا
for people with narcissistic personality disorder
للأفراد المصابين بالاضطراب النرجسي لشخصياتهم
to keep working at self-betterment.
ليستمروا بالعمل على تطوير أنفسهم.
For a narcissist, self-reflection is hard from an unflattering angle.
بالنسبة للنرجسي فإن انعكاس الذات صعب من زاويته اللامتملقة.